Okay, בוקר טוב. boker tov. We start now with today's דף כז,
daf kaf zayin, but we started at the bottom of כו עמוד
ב, kaf vav amud bet, and let's take a look as we
wrap up this במה איש שדה אחוזה. b'ma ish s'dei achuza. So
the mishna says the following: הלוקח שדה מאביו ומת אביו. Halokeach sodeh
mei-aviv u-meis aviv. Somebody,
now as we know, if you're the owner, you can redeem your
own field and keep it. And we actually learned you add a
fifth. That if the son redeems the field, then the owners get
to keep it. I should actually mention also that I came across
an interesting רמב"ם Rambam ראב"ד Ra'avad last night because our mishna read
that if somebody else redeemed it and you bought it off of
that person, you the original owner bought it off the person that
redeemed it, it doesn't matter. Once you were not the first person
to buy it off of הקדש, hekdesh, you've lost it when the
יובל yovel rolls around. But the רמב"ם Rambam actually rules opposite. The
רמב"ם Rambam says that if somebody else redeemed it and you bought
it off of him, so when the יובל yovel rolls around you're
in possession of it, then you get to keep it, which is
good, it gives the owners another option to keep it. The ראב"ד
Ra'avad says how could you say this? It's against an explicit mishna.
And then the ראב"ד Ra'avad says, then I checked all of the
various manuscripts and I actually saw that there was a manuscript to
the mishna that said what the רמב"ם Rambam said. So it's actually
quite fascinating. What? The ראב"ד Ra'avad says that.
Yeah, sure. I mean we all say in, I mean all they
had was manuscripts. It's not like they said we're going to put
aside the printed edition and look at the manuscripts.
Oh, and I understood that they were fairly rare, so...
Yeah, but not so rare. I have one and my, you know,
three other people in the town have a גמרא. Gemara. Those are
three other manuscripts. So anyway, so that's quite interesting. It also points
to the fact, you know, about how little of this is fleshed
out in the גמרא, Gemara, you know,
because it's like all these areas that aren't relevant nowadays. So anyway,
so if I buy my own field back or if my son
buys it back or according to the רמב"ם Rambam even if I
buy it off of somebody who bought it, I get to keep
it. Now, here's a scenario with the son that isn't exactly that.
Let's take a look at what the mishna says. הלוקח שדה מאביו
ומת אביו. Halokeach sodeh mei-aviv u-meis aviv.
So somebody purchased a field from his father. ראובן Reuven purchased a
field from יעקב, Yaakov, and then יעקב Yaakov died. ואחר כך הקדישה.
Ve-achar kach hikdisha. And then ראובן Reuven sanctified it. So now, what's
the status of this field? Is it a purchased field because initially
it was purchased, or is it a שדה אחוזה, sdei achuza, a
field of inheritance, right? A field because obviously even if he hadn't
purchased it from יעקב, Yaakov, he would have inherited it. So because
he would have inherited it regardless, therefore the הלכה halacha is we
treat it as a שדה אחוזה. sdei achuza. הרי היא כשדה אחוזה.
Harei hi k'sdei achuza. It's treated like a שדה אחוזה sdei achuza
because, you know, even if he hadn't done the purchase, it would
have been a שדה אחוזה sdei achuza and therefore he is entitled
to buy it back and redeem it and keep it when the
יובל yovel hits. הקדישה ואחר כך מת אביו. Hikdisha ve-achar kach meis
aviv.
Now here's a more complicated case. Let's say he purchased it, sanctified
it, and then his father died, and then the יובל yovel hit.
So at the moment of sanctifying it, his relationship to it was
only that of a purchased field, not of an inherited field. But
when the יובל yovel hits, at this stage it would have been
an inherited field. So how do you determine its status? At the
moment of sanctifying or the moment when the יובל yovel hits? So
it says, הרי היא כשדה מקנה דברי רבי מאיר. Harei hi k'sdei
miknah divrei Rabbi Meir. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says it's like a
purchased field. At the moment of sanctifying it, he did not inherit
it, and therefore it is a purchased field. רבי יהודה ורבי שמעון
אומרים, Rabbi Yehuda ve-Rabbi Shimon omrim, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon say, הרי היא כשדה אחוזה. Harei hi k'sdei achuza.
No, it's like an inherited field. שנאמר אם משדה מקנתו אשר לא
משדה אחוזתו. Shene'emar im misdei miknato asher lo misdei achuzato.
If from a purchased field which is not an inherited field. That's
a little redundant, because it's a purchased field. So obviously there's a
case which could be both purchased and inherited. And what is that?
That's this case. שדה שאינה ראויה להיות שדה אחוזה. sodeh she-eina re'uya
lihyot sdei achuza. Only if the purchased field that cannot become an
inherited field. יצא זו שהיא ראויה להיות שדה אחוזה. Yatza zo she-hi
re'uya lihyot sdei achuza. Which excludes this, which when the son purchased
it, fine, at that moment it was purchased, but he was in
line to inherit it and therefore it is treated as an inherited
field. Now, it's not clear if they would take this the whole
way, because if they would take this the whole way, then it
would even be true if the יובל yovel hit before the father
died, right? Because still his relationship to it, which would be bizarre,
because if some bought the field off the father, the father's alive,
and the יובל yovel hits, then you would want the father to
get it back, right? Of course, I think, but that's if he
didn't sanctify, right? I mean, look at the scenario. Son buys a
field off his father, doesn't sanctify it, יובל yovel hits. So you
would think that the father should get it back in that case,
right? Because he's still alive, he should still get it back, it's
the יובל. yovel. Son buys the field, sanctifies it, and the father's
alive. So actually, everybody loses out if you treat it as a
שדה מקנה, sdei miknah, because what happens if it's a שדה מקנה?
sdei miknah?
So then, oh no, no, I'm sorry, I'm sorry. Wait, wait. What's
the הלכה, halacha, right? Excuse me, excuse me. What's the הלכה halacha
if you buy a field off of somebody when the יובל yovel
is נוהג noheig and you sanctify it? You're only in a position
to sanctify it for the years remaining to the יובל yovel because
you never had a full purchase. Right. So if the father hasn't
died and the son purchased it and sanctified it, again, you would
logically think it should go back to the father, it shouldn't go
back to the son. So we don't read the דרשה drasha that
if he's in line for it to be a שדה אחוזה... sdei
achuza... It's like a שדה אחוזה sedei achuza to the extreme case.
Because that would obviously be unfair, that would mean that he could
buy it off his father, sanctify it, and he would get it
back, right, after the יובל Yovel even though he only had rights
for it for 20 years. So what we read is that so
we limit it to the case when the father actually dies. So
the father is now dead, and when he sanctified it he was
in line to inherit it, and now it's appropriate for him to
get it back, in this case we treat it as a שדה
אחוזה sedei achuza and he gets it back. Okay, so that's that
case. That's at least according to רבי יהודה ורבי שמעון. Rabbi Yehuda
ve-Rabbi Shimon.
Okay, now שדה מקנה, sedei mikna, now of course all along we've
been assuming the law about a purchased field but we haven't said
it, so now we're going to say it. שדה מקנה אינה יוצאה
לכהנים ביובל, Sedei mikna einah yotzah la-kohanim be-Yovel, if you purchase a
field and sanctify it, the כהנים kohanim don't get it. It goes
back to the original owner. שאין אדם מקדיש דבר שאינו שלו, She-ein
adam makdish davar she-eino shelo, because, I mean, you could have just
said it's a פסוק, pasuk, but it's actually quite a fascinating משנה.
Mishna. It takes a פסוק pasuk and translates it into rabbinic terms
and gives you the rabbinic legal reason why. Why when I sanctify
a field that I purchased it goes back to the original owners?
Because I only owned it until the יובל, Yovel, it was essentially
only a lease, and I can't sanctify more than I own. So
I can't make it go out of the possession of the owner.
So then when the יובל Yovel hits, it goes back to the
original owner. Okay, so that's wrapping up the issue of the שדה
מקנה, sedei mikna, what we've been assuming all along. Fascinating case about
a son buying it from his father. If the father first dies,
then we treat it as an inherited field. If the father never
dies, then obviously it's only a שדה מקנה, sedei mikna, not fair
to take it away from the father. But if he bought it,
sanctified it, and then the father died, then there's a debate whether
to treat it as a purchased or inherited field since he was
in line to inherit. One last line now of this משנה. Mishna.
הכהנים והלוויים מקדישים לעולם וגואלים לעולם. Ha-kohanim ve-ha-Levi'im makdishim le-olam ve-go'alim le-olam.
The כהנים kohanim and לוויים Levi'im can sanctify forever and redeem forever,
בין לפני היובל בין לאחר היובל, bein lifnei ha-Yovel bein le-achar ha-Yovel,
whether it's before or after the יובל. Yovel. Now what exactly that
means and in what way is that different from ישראל, Yisrael, we
will talk about in the גמרא, Gemara, but I just want to
point out that this is referring to a פסוק pasuk because the
פסוק pasuk says וערי הלוויים בתי ערי אחוזתם גאולת עולם תהיה ללוויים.
Ve-arei ha-Levi'im batei arei achuzatam ge'ulat olam tihyeh la-Levi'im. When it comes
to the cities of the לוויים, Levi'im, this is in בהר Behar
now, not בחוקותי, Bechukotai, thank you though. That when the cities of
the לוויים, Levi'im, they can always redeem it. Now in the context
there, it means that if somebody, if I sell my apartment in
a city and somebody else buys it, then I only have a
year to redeem it. And after that year, I've lost it, I
can't redeem it.
Okay, that's not true by the cities of the לוי. Levi. Even
after they sold it, whatever, they can always redeem it. But the
גמרא Gemara here is applying that, the משנה Mishna here is applying
that presumably to even fields, not houses in cities, and we will
see in the גמרא Gemara how it interprets this idea that the
לוויים Levi'im and כהנים kohanim can always redeem. Okay, so first we're
going to start about the case of buying it from one's father.
Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan,
we taught. מניין ללוקח שדה מאביו והקדישה? Minayin le-loke'ach sedeh me-aviv ve-hikdishah?
How do you know if somebody purchases a field from his father
and sanctifies it? ואחר כך מת אביו, Ve-achar kach met aviv, and
then his father died? So when he sanctified it, it was only
a purchased field. מניין שתהא לפניו כשדה אחוזה? Minayin she-tehei lefanav ke-sedei
achuza? How do you know that nevertheless it's treated as a bequeathed
field? תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, ואם את שדה מקנתו אשר לא משדה
אחוזתו. Ve-im et sedeh miknato asher lo mi-sedei achuzato.
If a purchased field that is not inherited, which is redundant. What's
the purpose of the second phrase? To tell you שדה שאינה ראויה
להיות שדה אחוזה. Sedeh she-einah re'uyah lihyot sedei achuza. Only if you
weren't in line to inherit. יצאה זו שראויה להיות שדה אחוזה, Yatzah
zu she-re'uyah lihyot sedei achuza, which excludes this case that although you
purchased it, you were in line to inherit and as we said,
the father is now dead, parenthetically. There, therefore it's treated as an
inherited field and you have a right to redeem it at the
הוזלה hozala forever. דברי רבי יהודה. Divrei Rabbi Yehuda. That's what רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says. ודברי רבי יהודה ורבי שמעון, Ve-divrei Rabbi Yehuda
ve-Rabbi Shimon, excuse me, that's what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon say. רבי מאיר
אומר, Rabbi Meir omer,
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says, מניין ללוקח שדה מאביו ומת אביו ואחר
כך הקדישה מניין שתהא לפניו כשדה אחוזה? Minayin le-loke'ach sedeh me-aviv u-met
aviv ve-achar kach hikdishah minayin she-tehei lefanav ke-sedei achuza? No, I'm only
saying that if the father died before you sanctified it, then it's
like an inherited field. תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, ואם משדה מקנתו אשר
לא משדה אחוזתו. Ve-im mi-sedeh miknato asher lo mi-sedei achuzato. שדה שאינה
שדה אחוזה. Sedeh she-einah sedei achuza. So what we exclude is a
purchased field that is not right now an inherited field. Meaning not
something that you're in line to inherit. It was purchased and inherited,
that's like it's inherited. The guy bought it and then his father
died. Then we don't say the fact that you purchased overrides the
fact that it's also inherited. Since it's also inherited, we treat it
as an inherited field. Okay, שתהא שדה אחוזה. She-tehei sedei achuza. But
if you, if the guy purchased it and sanctified it and then
the father died, so at the moment he sanctified it, it was
only purchased, it wasn't yet inherited although it was in line to
be, that's a שדה מקנה sedei mikna that is not a שדה
אחוזה. sedei achuza. Now of course, I'm trying to, I'm trying to
think this through, what would be the הלכה halacha then? The father
died, the guy purchased it, it's treated as a שדה מקנה, sedei
mikna, so when the יובל Yovel hits, it goes back to the
original owner. So who's the original owner? The father. Right, the father
who's dead. So it's inherited by his children. So he's going to
inherit it anyway. So I'm trying to figure out what the difference
is, is if you say that he keeps it straight. I guess
the difference is is if he has brothers. If it goes to
the father, then it'll be divided by all of the heirs, where
if you treat it now as his שדה אחוזה, sedei achuza, right,
although and then that actually puts the חידוש, chiddush, shows you the
חידוש chiddush of the position of רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, because according
to, according to what's-his-name, רבי יהודה ורבי שמעון... Rabbi Yehuda ve-Rabbi Shimon...
Even if I wouldn't have inherited the whole part, even if I
just would have been one of the heirs, the fact, that's enough
to give me my status as the owner and to mean that
when the יובל Yovel comes I keep it. So it's actually, you
know, if we're understanding it correctly, you know, then it's quite a
חידוש. chidush. It's not just that I would have inherited the whole
thing, but I would have been one of the heirs, presumably is
enough to designate me as an owner. Okay, because you have to
figure it out, because or else if you don't say that, then
it's hard to see what difference it would make if since it's
going to go to the father and back to the son anyway.
All right, so let's take a look. What? ודילמא דבסוף דכרת?
V'dilma d'besof d'karat?
Right,
so that would be another scenario if he's a בכור. bechor. But
all of those would point, but if he is the only heir,
I can't really see what a difference it would be. And אלא
לעולם, ela l'olam, it could be that he
מת meis before יובל Yovel himself and it would go to the
child.
Okay,
don't go there, I'm lost already. Okay, anyway, anyway, but presumably the
difference is when there are other brothers, which just really re-underscores the
position of רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda and רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon that
even though he wouldn't have been the only heir, the fact that
he was an heir is enough to have defined him as the
owner. Let's see where the גמרא Gemara goes with this. Okay,
now the גמרא Gemara says like this: לימא ובהא קמיפלגי. Leima uv'ha
kamifligi. Let's say they debate the following case. What is the debate
really, really, really rooted in? Meaning since you can read the verse
one way or the other way, there's nothing to indicate one read
over the other, maybe it's rooted in a deeper debate of some
legal distinction. רבי מאיר סבר, Rebbe Meir savar, רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir
would hold קנין פירות כקנין הגוף דמי, kinyan peiros k'kinyan haguf dami,
that if you own something just for the produce, it's like you
own the field itself. ורבי יהודה ורבי שמעון סברי, V'Rebbe Yehuda v'Rebbe
Shimon savri, and רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda and רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon
hold קנין פירות לאו כקנין הגוף דמי. kinyan peiros lav k'kinyan haguf
dami. No, it's not like you own the thing itself. What does
that mean? It means the son buys it from his father. Now
because the יובל Yovel is נוהג, noheig, it really is not a
purchase, it's really effectively a twenty-year lease or thirty-year lease, however many
years till the יובל. Yovel. Okay, so the son's relationship to this
land is a קנין פירות. kinyan peiros. He doesn't own this land
completely, he owns the land for the sake of its produce. Okay,
it's not like he just bought the fruit, he bought the land,
but he doesn't own the land outright, he owns it for its
produce for the next twenty years. That's קנין פירות. kinyan peiros. Now,
therefore, if we're saying that רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda and רבי שמעון
Rebbe Shimon would hold it's לאו כקנין הגוף. lav k'kinyan haguf. If
I therefore, I bought it, the guy, ראובן Reuven bought it from
his father, but it's not considered like he really has the title
yet, he only has a קנין פירות, kinyan peiros, he only has
a lease, he doesn't have the title yet. Then what happens? So
if he doesn't have the title yet, then his father,
then his father dies, now he has the title, now he sanctifies
it. So according to them, do you need a פסוק pasuk to
tell me in that scenario that we treat it as a שדה
אחוזה? sdei achuza? Of course not. First the guy only had a
lease, now he has a title, and now he sanctifies it, of
course it's
a
שדה אחוזה. sdei achuza. He only got the title as a שדה
אחוזה. sdei achuza. So what do you need the פסוק pasuk for?
You need the פסוק pasuk for when he had a lease, he
sanctified it, and then the father died, to say that even when
he sanctified it, we're going to treat it as a שדה אחוזה.
sdei achuza. But according to רבי מאיר, Rebbe Meir, he would say
no, I need the פסוק pasuk for the first case, because I
think even when you had a lease, it's as if he had
a title, and therefore, although his father now dies, maybe you still
define it as a שדה מקנה sdei mikna because that was his
first relationship to it and it really was as if he had
the title. So therefore you need the פסוק pasuk to tell me
the simpler case, because I wouldn't even know the simpler case. So
do you understand the difference here? Meaning this issue of קנין פירות
כקנין הגוף kinyan peiros k'kinyan haguf is not directly how that would
have translated into this scenario, it's what case I would have needed
the verse for. If I would have said if you say that
my first relationship to the land is only a lease and not
a title, then you don't need the verse to tell me the
case when he first had the lease and then the father died
and then he sanctified, that's obviously the important, you go by when
the father died. And that's רבי יהודה ורבי שמעון. Rebbe Yehuda v'Rebbe
Shimon. So they need the case for a more extreme case, sanctified
and then the father died. Whereas according to the other opinion, רבי
מאיר, Rebbe Meir, he would say no, even in the first case
it's not so obvious, when you had the lease it's as if
you had the title, so maybe it's not like a שדה אחוזה.
sdei achuza. So therefore he needs it for the first scenario, he's
not able to get yet to the second scenario. So that's what
the גמרא Gemara suggests. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר
רב נחמן בר יצחק, Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, no, בעלמא לרבי
שמעון ורבי יהודה קנין פירות כקנין הגוף דמי. b'alma l'Rebbe Shimon v'Rebbe
Yehuda kinyan peiros k'kinyan haguf dami. You're not forced to say that.
They could really hold that a lease and rights to the produce
or whatever, purchasing it for a limited time is like a title.
So if it's like a title, then why don't I need the
פסוק pasuk to tell me the simpler case? First you have the
lease, then the father died. Since the lease is like a title,
maybe it's defined as a שדה מקנה, sdei mikna, not a שדה
אחוזה. sdei achuza. דהכא קרא אשכח ודרש. D'hacha kra ashcach v'darash.
Here it really is what you were trying to avoid to say,
it's too bad Michael isn't here, because very often Michael is very
focused on the hermeneutics and I try to say, well, often there's
another thing that's pushing them. So here the גמרא Gemara says, "No,
really is a hermeneutic debate." Here it's they would have, left to
their own devices, have said you need a פסוק Pasuk to tell
me even the first case,
purchase like lease, but the פסוק Pasuk pushes them to say the
second case. Why? קרא אשכח ודרש. Kra ashkhach ve'darash. לכתוב רחמנא אם
משדה מקנה אשר לא שדה אחוזה. Likhtov Rachmana im mi'sdei mikne asher
lo sdei achuza.
Why did it need the extra mem? Let's say if it's a
purchased field that is not an inherited field, and that would have
told me the case of
purchase and then the father dies, because then it is an inherited
field as well. אי נמי I nami אשר לא שדה
אחוזה asher lo sdei achuza or no, אחוזה achuza rather than אחוזתו.
achuzato. מאי משדה אחוזתו? Mai mi'sdei achuzato?
What's the extra mem doing? שדה שאינה ראויה להיות שדה אחוזה. Sadeh
she'eina re'uya lihyot sdei achuza. It's saying we're not only excluding the
first case, a purchase dies sanctify, that would have been excluded by
the verse that said a purchase field that's not a inherited, and
that case it's also an inherited and that would have addressed that
case. The extra mem that says a purchase field that is not
from an inherited field means that it's not even from a field
that's in line to become an inherited field, and that extra mem
pushes us to the case of buying, sanctifying, and then the father
dies. מאי משדה אחוזתו? Mai mi'sdei achuzato? שדה שאינה ראויה להיות שדה
אחוזה, Sadeh she'eina re'uya lihyot sdei achuza, יצא זו שראויה להיות שדה
אחוזה. yatza zu she're'uya lihyot sdei achuza. Okay,
so in the end though the גמרא Gemara does not really says
it's all about how you interpret the verse, does not really say
that it translates into some bigger legal debate. Okay, and we have
this question again if somebody purchases, it sanctifies, the father dies, since
now he was in line to be a שדה אחוזה, sdei achuza,
is that enough to שדה אחוזה sdei achuza to say that he
can keep it, or no, does it go back as it were
to the father and get re-divided by the all of the heirs?
Okay, so that's one debate. Let's now wrap this up about the
כהנים ולויים גואלין לעולם. Kohanim ve'Levi'im go'alin le'olam. What does that exactly
mean in the context here about fields?
So the גמרא Gemara says like this: בשלמא גואלין איצטריך. Bishlama go'alin
itztarich. I understand that you say that the כהנים Kohanim can redeem
forever, that's telling me something important. לאפוקי מישראל דלא פרקי. Le'afukei mi'Yisrael
de'lo parkei. To exclude a normal ישראל Yisrael who cannot redeem. Now,
what does this mean? What is the scenario that a normal ישראל
Yisrael cannot redeem his field? I sanctify my field, what's the scenario
that I cannot redeem it?
No, no, no, I sanctify my field and then what happens? Then,
then somebody else buys it, right? And then יובל Yovel comes around,
right? Then I've lost it. I can't redeem it. Let's say nobody
else bought it, okay, and then יובל Yovel comes around, then that's
debated, right? If nobody buys it and יובל Yovel comes around, that
might also be that it goes to the כהנים Kohanim or I
might still have an option according to רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. So
now we're saying the כהנים Kohanim can redeem it. Do we mean
both cases? I actually this is why I was looking at the
רמב"ם Rambam last night. The רמב"ם Rambam isn't clear about that. The
second case is easier. The second case is the כהנים Kohanim sanctified
it. So we could say, if a ישראל Yisrael sanctified it and
nobody purchased it, it goes to the כהנים, Kohanim, right, according to
not רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, right? It would go to the כהנים
Kohanim if nobody purchased it. If the כהנים Kohanim sanctified it and
nobody purchased it, maybe it doesn't go to the כהנים, Kohanim, maybe
I still have a right to repurchase it at any time. Okay,
that would be that scenario. It's not so clear the other scenario.
The other scenario is the more common one. I sanctify it, somebody
buys it, it goes to the כהנים. Kohanim. So would we say
that by the כהנים Kohanim that also is not true? That I,
the כהן, Kohen, sanctify it, somebody buys it, the יובל Yovel hits,
it doesn't go to the כהנים. Kohanim. So what does גואלין לעולם
go'alin le'olam mean? גואלין לעולם Go'alin le'olam means that I can go
to the guy who bought it off of הקדש Hekdesh and force
him to sell it back to me? That's not classic גואלין. go'alin.
Classic גואלין go'alin is I redeem it back off of הקדש, Hekdesh,
right? So what so that's is not so clear to me and
it wasn't so clear in the רמב"ם. Rambam. The first scenario is
a lot easier. It remains in the hands of הקדש Hekdesh after
יובל Yovel and I can always and it doesn't go to the
כהנים Kohanim and I, the כהן, Kohen, can always re-redeem it back.
But if somebody else purchased it, it's not clear to me that
that would be the case of גואלין לעולם go'alin le'olam because גואלין
go'alin is normally from הקדש. Hekdesh. So what would we say? We
would say maybe that the יובל Yovel hits and rather than going
to the כהנים, Kohanim, it now just goes to the hands of
the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and is ready for me to redeem
it when I want to. So these things are not so clear.
What did you want to say though?
Use of the term כהן, Kohen, individual כהן Kohen and כהנים Kohanim
as interchangeable. Uh-huh. But just because the כהנים Kohanim get it doesn't
mean the specific כהן Kohen who sold it in the first place
sanctified it in the first place.
So you think גואלין לעולם go'alin le'olam means that another כהן Kohen
can redeem?
Yeah, so it actually raises the question, what does it mean it
goes to the כהנים? Kohanim? Is there like communal property of the
כהנים? Kohanim? Does it go to a specific כהן? Kohen?
Yeah, so רש"י Rashi so there's another גמרא Gemara that basically says,
which as I mentioned before, that it gets divided by the כהנים,
Kohanim, actually does get divvied up by the כהנים Kohanim that happen
to be lucky enough to have their week during the יום כיפור
Yom Kippur when the יובל Yovel falls out. But I thought you
were saying something else. I thought you were saying that גואלין לעולם
go'alin le'olam meant if I'm a כהן Kohen and I sanctify it
and you're a כהן, Kohen, you can redeem it even after the
יובל. Yovel. Not just I can redeem it after the יובל, Yovel,
or at least we both can, but maybe I still have precedence
as the original owner, but at least it's not just referring to
the כהן Kohen who's the original owner. That's a fascinating possibility as
well.
``` In []: ```python
# check the length of
the
transcription len(transcription) ``` Out []: ```output 24971 ``` In []: ```python #
save the
transcription to
a
file with
open('transcription.txt', 'w') as f: f.write(transcription) ``` of
fifty שקל shekel for
a
certain size of for a certain acreage is only when there are
all the laws of יובל Yovel and that there's a fixed amount
of time.
So if there's no יובל, Yovel, that's not the that's not the
chart that you use. So how do you determine how much how
to redeem it? So you go by its market value. Now, how
do you determine its market value? So you might have said that
okay, you sanctify it, בית דין Beis Din now will get some
assessors to come and determine its market value, and anybody who wants
to redeem it, you know, can go ahead and redeem it. I
want to point out to you what are the consequences of the
יובל Yovel not being נוהג. noheg. Number one is market value, as
I said. Number two is on the one
if I'm the owner and I didn't redeem it, okay, when the
יובל Yovel runs comes around, if somebody else purchased it or even
if nobody purchased it, I you know who you know
I don't get it back, it transfers to the כהנים, Kohanim, right,
you know, and that's it, it's out of my control. However, if
the יובל Yovel isn't נוהג noheg and and I'm the owner and
I sanctified it, so it's still in the hands of the בית
המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, I can still redeem it, right? Somebody else can
too, but I still have at least a shot at redeeming it.
If somebody else purchased it, I sanctified my field, יובל Yovel isn't
נוהג, noheg, somebody else bought it off the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash,
David here bought it off the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, what happens?
Nothing. יובל Yovel comes, what do you mean יובל Yovel comes? There
is no יובל. Yovel. David's now the owner. So if I ever
want to get the field back, I have to have I have
to try to get have a deal with David. So on the
one hand, it doesn't get transferred to the כהנים Kohanim or whatever,
on the right,
but on the other you know, but but the point is is
that now so no I mean number one so let's just read
that. Number one is it goes by market value. Number two is
יובל Yovel is irrelevant. So I sanctify it, I have an option
to buy it back as long as it's still in the possession
of the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, okay, but it the
and it's not until the יובל, Yovel, there's no יובל Yovel that
changes that. So I have that option as long as it's in
possession, but other people can also try to buy it off the
בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. And if I and if the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash actually sold it to somebody, then I have to try
to buy it off him. So basically, it's the way we do
the point is when there's no יובל, Yovel, it's the way we
do with property nowadays, okay? If I if I sanctified my car
to the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, what's the הלכה halachah if I
sanctified my car to the בית המקדש? Beis HaMikdash? I can try
to buy it back off of them before somebody else does, and
if I don't and they sold it to somebody, then I have
to try to get it off the other person. There's nothing special
about it. You might as well have sanctified your car, and that
is when there isn't why is there no יובל? Yovel? So could
be there's no בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, although I'll get to that
in a minute, or it could just be that it's in the
period in the period of the second בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, so
I'll get to that in a second. In the period of the
second בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, because most of the inhabitants were not
on the land and it was not divided according to the tribes,
there is no יובל Yovel even though there was a בית המקדש.
Beis HaMikdash. So since James raises that so let's read then the
משנה Mishnah and then I want to get back to James's question,
okay? But that's the point. Market value and it might as well
be an automobile, okay? I can try to buy it back, but
so can other people. The one difference is that because I've sanctified
my thing, if I want to buy back my thing, and this
would be true in the תורה Torah says even by your house,
if you sanctify your house, you sanctify your car, you want to
buy it back off the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, you have to
add a חומש. chomesh. So that is the one way but it's
not about the its specialness about being a field, okay? There's no
יובל, Yovel, בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash has it, they can do with
it whatever they want, I can try to buy it back if
I'm lucky enough to from בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, if somebody else
purchased it, but it's all first come first served. The only thing
is that I have to add a חומש. chomesh.
What? שדה אחוזה? Sedeh Achuzah?
There's no more שדה אחוזה, Sedeh Achuzah, right. It's like סתם מקדיש,
stam makdish, it's like not even a field. Okay, now, so אומר
לו, omer lo, so we say to the owner, פתח אתה ראשון,
ptach atah rishon, you make the first offer. Why do we want
the owners to make the first offer? Because whatever number they say,
they're going to have to add a חומש chomesh to it. So
if there's going to be a bidding war, we'd rather give preference
to the owner's bid and give let give them get a first
shot because he's going to have to add a חומש. chomesh. Now,
of course, if you're a smart owner, you're going to take what
you would have paid and deduct the חומש, chomesh, but of course
then you're likely to be outbid. So this is the way it
works. In order to win in order to win the bidding war,
you have to have a higher number in terms of the principal.
But once you win, then you're going to have to add the
חומש, chomesh, okay? So that's why we want the owner to get
into the into the debate and
this is another market value. This חומש chomesh is on on right.
So that is the other thing that is a big חידוש chiddush
of this משנה, Mishnah, is that you would have assumed, right, and
thank you, that's what I was going to say, you would have
assumed that we just assess the market value and now whoever wants
to buy it at this value, come and do it, and if
the owner does, it's the חומש chomesh of that. But no, actually
it becomes an auction. It becomes a bidding war, okay? And therefore
we want the owner to suggest because now for him to win,
he both has a higher base and he's going to add a
חומש. chomesh. Yeah, it's a big deal. Right. Okay, but that's the
point. We the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash don't set the value, it
becomes an auction.
Okay, what's what's the value for him to have the first bid?
I know, it's really true.
What's the advantage? Well, it's he has a buy buy-out rate.
Yeah, it's really true. We'll see as it goes on. It's, you
know, it's more like maybe other people aren't even interested. So you're
right though, if he's, you know, or once he gets into it
the auction, then maybe he'll continue being into it. But you're right,
it's not so clear. The basic point is... We want the owner
to make an offer. Whether we're going to take that offer or
not, but we want him to get into the bidding. We want
him to be making an offer. Right.
Also for market value and that would end it.
No, as we're going to see, we still are interested in what
the other offers are. Yes.
Whose job is it? Are there כהנים Kohanim who evaluate? I mean,
or...
Yes.
So normally there would be a, actually, ten people that would assess
the value and so on. But that is, you know, that is
when the יובל Yovel is נוהג, noheg, there are those sort of
formalities. When the יובל Yovel is not נוהג, noheg, it goes much
more here by this bidding war.
Okay. I wonder how much this is helpful for an עני ani
to be able to give in a meaningful way if, I mean,
they're not an עני, ani, but they own land. Right.
Why would anyone just not be מקדיש דמיו, makdish damav, right? Like,
מקדיש דמיו makdish damav and be done with it? It's a fixed
rate, the market rate, or whatever else, and
he's done, he doesn't have to worry about adding the extra fifth,
he doesn't have to worry, especially if he's going to want it
back. So the basic, this inclination to want the owner to be
involved in the bidding, the only way it's to his advantage is
if he can somehow bid less than the value of the field.
He couldn't actually...
So we're actually going to see that. We're going to see that
in a minute. That's true. So let's take a look. Okay. All
right. So now, okay. שהבעלים נותנים חומש וכל אדם אינם נותנים חומש.
she-be-alim notnim chomesh ve-chol adam einam notnim chomesh. מעשה באחד שהקדיש שדהו
מפני רעתה. ma'aseh be-echad she-hikdish sadeh mipnei ra'atah. Now there was a,
why, I'm sorry, I didn't finish the line. שהבעלים נותנים חומש וכל
אדם אינם נותנים חומש. she-be-alim notnim chomesh ve-chol adam einam notnim chomesh.
Now, מעשה באחד שהקדיש שדהו מפני רעתה. ma'aseh be-echad she-hikdish sadeh mipnei
ra'atah. Somebody sanctified a field because of its bad quality, meaning, as
רש"י Rashi says, it's not, you don't even, you know, it's not
even worth the expenses. It's so bad that no matter how much,
you know, you don't, you make no profit off of it. So
what, what good is it going to do? So he sanctified it.
He was able to do his gesture, even it didn't cost him
anything, he wasn't getting anything from the field anyway. אמרו לו, amru
lo, they said to him, פתח אתה ראשון. petach atah rishon. Make
an offer. How much would you like to buy it back? He
does, oh, there was a real nice way to find it, but
okay. They say to make an offer. אמר, amar, okay, הרי שלי
באיסר. harei sheli be-issar. Fine, a dollar. So אמרו לו, amru lo,
אמר רבי יוסי, amar Rabbi Yose, הרי שלי באיסר. harei sheli be-issar.
אמר רבי יוסי, amar Rabbi Yose, לא אמר זה באיסר אלא בביצה.
lo amar zeh be-issar ela be-beitzah. He said,
okay, fine, I'll give an egg to get it back. So שהקדש
נפדה בכסף ובשוה כסף, she-hekdesh nifdeh be-kesef u-ve-shaveh kesef,
because even you can redeem it even with equivalent, you don't have
to redeem it with cash, it can even be with anything of
value. אמרו לו, amru lo, what?
That's less than the smallest denomination.
Well, we'll talk, yeah, so it has to be at least a
פרוטה, perutah, but the גמרא Gemara is going to say that there's
not, that the fifth won't become a פרוטה perutah according to רבי
יוסי. Rabbi Yose. That's the חידוש chiddush of a ביצה. beitzah. But
it does presumably have to be a פרוטה. perutah. אמרו לו, amru
lo,
so they said to him, הגטיעך, higti'acha, deal! נמצא מפסיד את שדהו
לפניו. nimtza mafsid et sadehu lefanav.
So
you didn't accomplish anything, you still had to pay your buck, and
you didn't get rid of your field! So the point of this
seems to be, now, A, number one, to really show that it
is about a bid and not about הקדש, hekdesh, about somebody setting
a value, you know, about הקדש hekdesh assessing a value, but number
two, that we not only ask you to bid first, we sort
of pressure you to bid first. Right, that seems to be, and
the גמרא Gemara is going to discuss that. Because the point of
the משנה mishnah seems to be you were trying to get rid
of your field and we didn't let you do it. We sort
of made you make an offer, forced you to make an offer.
Didn't say forced, but like, pressured you. So let's take a look
at that episode in more detail.
I had a question before, what you were saying that
the gift was supposed to be eternal.
Yes, but in this is a, this is a case where, okay,
so let's take a look, this is a case where nobody wants
it, right? The, okay, so let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara. המקדיש שדהו בשעת אומן, amakdish sadehu be-sha'at omin, you say to
him, make an offer. והתניא כופין. ve-hatanya kofin. We have a ברייתא
baraita that says you force him to make an offer, which is
basically exactly this case. Okay. So מאי אומרים נמי? mai omrim nami?
So what does it mean you say, you say to him? כופין.
kofin. It means you force! You keep on saying and you don't
give him a choice to say no. Make him an offer he
can't refuse.
This prevents הקדש hekdesh from becoming the garbage dump. Exactly.
Well, that's exactly, that's a good point. And that's sort of the
larger, you know, so you're right, meaning on the one hand if
it's a worth, if it's a field that has value, you want
him to get in the bidding war because you want, if once
he's in the bid, you know, he might up the, you know,
we might get more money from him. But the other possibility is
exactly the first case of the משנה mishnah is emphasizing that, that
point, that you don't want it to be a garbage dump. Then
therefore you actually pressure him to at least make some offer if
it's in that scenario.
Okay. איבעית אימא, ibe'it eima, if you want you can say, מעיקרא
אומרים. me-ikara omrim. First you suggest, you say, make an offer. איציי
איציי, itzaye itzaye, if he takes the hint, good, and he makes
an offer. ואי לא, ve-ilo, and if he refuses to take it,
then כופין, kofin, then we'll twist his arm. But basically exactly that
we do not let people dump stuff on הקדש hekdesh if it's
worthless, we're going to pressure the owner to make even some trivial
offer and buy it back. We do not want stuff that's worthless.
But presumably the other thing is also true, that if it's worth
a serious value, then, you know, then we still want you to
be in the bid, in the bid.
Even if he wanted to give this eternal gift, you're making him
make an offer to buy it back.
Well, הקדש hekdesh has no, has no, has no interest. I mean,
they're not, right, they don't want to be landlords, they don't want
to be in the agricultural business and so on.
Hekdesh הקדש Hekdesh is now interested in getting the most money they
can out of it. Okay, so let's take a look. Oh, we
have an additional bid. So it's valuable. Right.
It's a market for somebody else. Right. הבעלים נותנים חמש, Shebe'alim notnim
chamesh, מאי איריא הבעלים נותנים חמש? mai irya shebe'alim notnim chamesh? Why
do you have to emphasize the owner should make the first bid
because he has a fifth? חדא דאיידי דחביבא ליה טפי הוא פריק
ליה. Chada de'aydi dechaviva lei tfei hu parik lei. First of all,
we should say that because he has a personal connection to it,
we would want him to be in the bidding war because he'll
probably offer more money
because he because
it
has
this sort
of
sentimental value and he has this connection to it. Of course you
could say maybe if he has such a sentimental value, he wants
to sacrifice. But fine, now that we're trying to, maybe as as
we were saying he was making a grand gesture, but now we're
trying to make money, and maybe he will and in this stage
actually offer more for the principal. ועוד, Ve'od, and even if moving
away from money, מצות גאולה באדון. mitzvat geulah ba'adon. The Torah says
if the owner doesn't redeem it and then somebody else buys it.
So it sets a priority, the owner is supposed to be the
first one to buy it back.
So חכמים Chachamim says, you know what, you're right. There are all
those reasons. חדא ועוד קאמר, Chada ve'od ka'amar, one and another. חדא,
Chada, number one, he should be involved in the bidding war, דאיידי
דחביבא ליה טפי הוא פריק ליה, de'aydi dechaviva lei tfei hu parik
lei, because it's dear to him he'll bid more money for it.
ועוד, Ve'od, and he should be involved in the bidding war because
מצות גאולה באדון, mitzvat geulah ba'adon, because
anyway he's supposed to have the first option, he's supposed to be
the first one to try to buy it back. The Torah says
if the owner redeems it and if the owner doesn't redeem it
and then somebody else buys it. So it's the first mitzvah's for
him to redeem it. ועוד שהבעלים נותנים חמש, Ve'od shebe'alim notnim chamesh,
and in addition to all of those, whatever bid he comes in
with, they'll have to add a fifth to it. What?
It's the language of mitzvah. Right.
Yes, and that's actually was a Mishnah earlier in, in, what do
you call it, in, not Erchin, what did we do before Erchin?
בכורות, Bechorot, that actually spoke about, you know, there's a mitzvah to
do yibum before chalitzah, a mitzvah to do this before that, and
one of the things was it's a mitzvah the owner to redeem
rather than somebody else. Okay.
Now, מעשה באחד שהקדיש שדהו, Ma'aseh be'echad shehikdish sadehu, ולימא בהא קמיפלגי?
uleima beha kamiflegi? What's this today? An egg or a dollar? Maybe
they debate the following. דרבי יוסי סבר, DeRabbi Yossi savar, is it
Rabbi Yossi? I forget who was in the Mishnah. Yeah, Rabbi Yossi.
דרבי יוסי סבר שוה כסף ככסף, DeRabbi Yossi savar shaveh kessef kekessef,
that even an equivalent you can redeem on. ורבנן סברי שוה כסף
אינו ככסף. Verabbanan savri shaveh kessef eino kekessef. No, you can only
redeem on cash. The Gemara said, no, you can't say that. הא
קיימא לן דשוה כסף ככסף. Ha kayma lan deshveh kessef kekessef. Everybody
agrees that you can redeem on money equivalent. So the Gemara says
fine, דכולי עלמא שוה כסף ככסף, dechulei alma shaveh kessef kekessef, everybody
agrees to that. והכא בפודה בדבר שאין בחומשו שוה פרוטה קמיפלגי. Vehacha
befodeh bedavar she'ein bechumsho shaveh perutah kamiflegi.
Now nobody wants to suggest what they thought, which is that the
actual egg was less than a perutah. That we can't accept. You
need at least a perutah to redeem something. But what if it's
only a perutah? Or what if the fifth that you add is
less than a perutah? It's like the fifth is less than a
penny. Can you allow for a scenario where the owner won't be
able to give the fifth because it is less than your smallest
coin? דתנא קמא סבר איסר, DeTanna Kamma savar issar, only if he
says an issar, דאיכא בחומשו שיעור פרוטה, de'ika bechumsho shiur perutah, because
an issar, I forget how many perutahs it is, but at least
more, at least it's four or more. So the, by the way,
a chomesh is a quarter of the base, so that when you
add the quarter, you have it's a fifth of the end. Okay,
so that at least you can add a fifth of that or
a quarter of that is a perutah. פרקינן, Parkinan, you can do
it. רבי יוסי, ביצה נמי פרקינן, Rabbi Yossi, beitzah nami parkinan, even
if it's only a perutah you can redeem it even if the
fifth is not a perutah. אמרו לו הגעתנו, Amru lo higatanu, נמצא
מפסיד איסר ובית שדהו לפניו. nimtza mafsid issar uveit sadehu lefanav.
So you'd have to pay your issar and take your field back,
your lousy field back.
סתמא דרבנן דאמר כאיסר, Stama deRabbanan de'amar ke'issar, and not the egg.
Now I want to go back to the question James raised, which
is, what's the scenario that there's no Yovel? So the easiest case
is that there's no Beit HaMikdash nowadays. Now although no Beit HaMikdash
you can't sanctify, it's not true, you can sanctify.
There's nobody around to collect, but if I go ahead with my
car and I say אני מקדיש את זה לבדק הבית. Ani makdish
et zeh levedek habayit. It is now because sanctity is not just
a question of like whose bank account it's in, but it's also
a question of it's its metaphysical status. And God is sort of
everywhere, and the rights of Hekdesh are everywhere. My car now has
קדושה kedushah and it's owned by the Beit HaMikdash, although there are
no officers that are going to come pick it up, but it's
owned by the entity of the Beit HaMikdash and it has sanctity.
Now, so it is possible, but תוספות Tosafot makes the point. תוספות
Tosafot says, ah, but if we were talking about no Beit HaMikdash,
since there's nobody to collect and there's no financial interest nowadays, I'm
allowed to redeem things even on a perutah. Meaning there would never
be a bidding war, it's just a person, it's just about getting
the קדושה kedushah off of it.
Right, it's about just about getting the קדושה kedushah off of it
because there's no actual financial interest that Hekdesh has. So if I
were to now sanctify my field, we wouldn't get to have any
bidding war. I would just take a perutah, I'd redeem it on
the perutah, I'd remove the קדושה kedushah symbolically, whatever, I'd remove the
קדושה kedushah and now I can use my field again. So the
case of the Mishnah has to be a special case. There's no
Yovel, but there is a Beit HaMikdash. Beit HaMikdash has a financial
interest. And תוספות Tosafot says that's the time period of the second
Beit HaMikdash. Second
Beit HaMikdash there was
Well, presumably not because they would only get their אחוזה *achuza* back
when the יובל *yovel* hit and there was no יובל *yovel* to
hit. It reverts at אחוזה *achuza*. No, tough luck. As long as
there's no יובל *yovel*, it doesn't revert to you.
But what if they owned it when they were in exile?
Oh, that's a political question. You know, I don't know, that's a
political question, it's not a halakhic question. Right, whether they, you know,
what did they do? Did they dispossess the people that were currently
there? They didn't have so much power when they initially came back.
Okay, it took a while till they got power.
So the case of the אחוזה *achuza* then is pointless even if
there was a בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash *Beis HaMikdash* and everyone was
back.
No, no, if you got to a state where, A, you were
willing to exert that political power and, B, the יובל *yovel* was
known, then you would have reverted the field.
To make everyone move back to the plots they had in the
first בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*?
Right.
Yeah, practically this couldn't happen.
All right, next משנה Mishnah *mishnah*. אמר אחד הרי היא שלי *Amar
echad harei hi sheli*. Now we're going to have the bidding war.
That's the owner had the first offer and nobody else wanted to
even be in it. Makes them offer, take it, goodbye, you have
to make an offer. Okay, next משנה Mishnah *mishnah*, bidding war. אמר
אחד הרי היא שלי בעשר סלעים *Amar echad harei hi sheli be-eser
sela'im*. I'll offer ten shekel. ואחד אמר בעשרים *Ve-echad amar be-esrim*, twenty.
ואחד אמר בשלושים *Ve-echad amar be-shloshim*, thirty. ואחד אמר בארבעים *Ve-echad amar
be-arba'im*, forty. ואחד אמר בחמישים *Ve-echad amar be-chamishim*, fifty. Okay, great. So
you give it to the guy that says fifty, obviously. Now we
have a problem, right? It's like, now we can totally identify with
this because we do it every day with eBay, right? So what
happens nowadays if basically somebody after they make the bid and they
win the auction, they change their mind? So if it's on eBay,
then you get a negative rating and nobody wants to have you
participate anymore. But what happens in this case? So the בית המקדש
*Beis HaMikdash*, here we have a fascinating point. Since this is being
done by a bidding war, the bids actually wind up determining how
we determine, how we sort of in some objective way say what
its value is. So the guy who said fifty essentially set its
value at fifty, not just that it was his offer. In some
objective way, he's defined the value as fifty. Now he backs out.
You're backing out and now its value is fifty. We're only going
to be able to get forty from the next guy. Your backing
out has now caused us to lose ten shekel. You have to
pay the ten shekel. Okay, so you pay the difference. You don't
get it, you backed
out, but because you've now decided or you've decided for us that
its value is fifty and you're not paying it, you're making us
lose ten out of its value.
But is the forty guy, his
total bid would be...
We're going to get to the bidding with the owner later.
Does the forty guy, the guy who bid forty, is he obligated
now to buy it?
Yes, and if he backs out, then he has to pay the
next difference. So that's what the משנה mishna, *mishnah*'s going to say.
חזר בו של חמישים *Chazar bo shel chamishim*, the fifty guy backed
out, ממשכנין מנכסיו עד עשר ad eser, *memashkenin minichasav ad eser*. You
make him, you basically, remember you had that when I wasn't here,
the whole idea about seizing his property. Okay, so even if he
doesn't want to pay, it doesn't matter, you go ahead and you
force him and you'll even seize his property to pay the ten
difference. חזר בו של ארבעים Chazar bo shel arbaim, *Chazar bo shel
arba'im*, now the forty guy backed out, ממשכנין מנכסיו עד עשר *memashkenin
minichasav ad eser*. Okay, so now he's causing us to lose ten
because now we only have to go to the thirty guy and
he set the value at forty. So, or so, you know, his
backing out was a loss of ten. חזר בו של שלושים *Chazar
bo shel shloshim*, thirty guy backed out, ממשכנין מנכסיו עד עשר *memashkenin
minichasav ad eser*. So he has to pay ten. וחזר בו של
עשרים *Ve-chazar bo shel esrim*, the twenty guy backed out, ממשכנין מנכסיו
עד עשר *memashkenin minichasav ad eser*. He pays ten because everybody's backing
out is making us lose the next ten. חזר בו של עשר
Chazar bo shel eser, *Chazar bo shel eser*, now the ten guy
backed out, he was the first bid. So what do we do
with him? So then מוכרין אותו בשוויה *mochrin oso beshavyah*. Now this
is interesting, right? Here we actually will now do it to have
a, do it, do it on a market, at a market rate.
We'll set the market value, first come gets it, buys it, no
more auction. Okay, so that's an option for us. Obviously we want
to do the auction if we can get more money off of
the auction, but there's always the option for us to sell it
at market value. So we sell it at market value and now
the guy who did ten, what does he cause us to lose?
The difference between ten and the market value.
Okay, ונפרעים של עשר את המותר et hamotar, *venifraim shel eser es
hamotar*.
So you get the difference from ten and the market price and
that goes from the last guy.
That's a big deterrent for participating in these auctions. You really put
yourself at risk.
Not if you're not, no, only if you're only if you're not
serious. If you're,
if you're, אדרבה *aderaba*, it just means that understand that all bids
are binding and once you've made a bid, you're going to have
to be committed to at least that bid. What it actually is
a deterrent for, here's what it's a deterrent for, which does happen
also on in auctions at eBay or whatever. It's for you're not
really interested in buying it, you're just trying to drive up the
price. That's what it's a deterrent for. Just be aware that any
bid you make is binding and we can always go to you
even if somebody else backs out. What?
Now, הבעלים אומרים בעשרים. Habealim omrim beesrim
Now we get to a debate, a competition with the owners because
owners are going to have a say. הבעלים habealim, אומרים בעשרים וכל
אדם אומרים בעשרים. vechol adam omrim beesrim. 20 and 20. Of course
we're going to go to the owners, they're going to add a
fifth. הבעלים קודמים מפני שהם מוסיפים חומש. Habealim kodmim mipnei shehem mosifim
chomesh. Number one, there's a mitzvah of הבעלים, habealim but also they're
going to get us more money. Now, אמר אחד הרי היא שלי
בעשרים ואחת. Amar echad harei hi sheli beesrim veachat. Here's a tough
thing to take. The owners say 20, somebody else says 21.
Now, if the הבעלים add a fifth, the fifth is really a
quarter because it's a quarter, it becomes a fifth at the end.
So their 20, their fifth will become 25. Okay,
right? Because then five is a fifth of 25. Okay, so הקדש
Hekdesh would rather go with the owner because he's going to get
25. But the other guy made a higher bid. So what do
you do? הבעלים נותנים עשרים ושש. Habealim notnim beesrim veshesh. So here
it's similar to, I'm going to explain, it's similar to the other
case where when somebody makes a bid, it's as if it automatically
sets the price. So here, on the one hand, you as the
owner, you won because you would have paid the higher final price.
On the other hand, so you're in principle the winner of this
auction. On the other hand, the other guy said 21, so he's
defined that the price is 21. So you won the auction, but
he gets to define the price. So he defined the price as
21, you pay 21, and then you have to add the fifth
to your initial bid. You don't add the fifth to 21, you
add the fifth to your initial bid, and therefore you wind up
paying 26.
Wait, then all he would pay is 20, so I don't understand
how they're forcing him to pay an extra shekel.
I understand, that's what I'm saying. It's not just as we think
of an auction, which is just an offer and it's meaningless until
it's accepted. What we have seen is, right, because you saw before,
the 40, the 30, all those types of things, that the offer
in a way designates the price. So on the one hand, this
guy made a higher bid, designated the price as 21, that was
a valid designation of the price. On the other hand, you as
the owner, you won the auction. So you wind up being committed
to more than you were prepared to pay? Yes. Okay, so that's
where I'm at. I understand, so you have to know the rules
of the game before going in. That's the only point.
Just know the rules of the game. Okay, so somebody else said
24. What? Then you have to add four more.
Keep on going.
Okay, so there's no incentive for the בעל baal not to drive
up the price for everybody else, as long as the בעל... baal...
Right, exactly, exactly. If you've got something, הקדש, Hekdesh, it's in הקדש's
Hekdesh interest to get somebody to bid against the בעל baal up
to a certain point because then it'll... the בעל baal really just
adds... the בעל baal has to know that, which is crazy because
then it really does put the בעלים bealim at a disadvantage. And
in whose interest is it to try to discourage the בעלים bealim
from participating in the bid? So
anyway, let's keep on going.
בעשרים ושתיים, Beesrim veshtayim, so somebody says 22 and he says 20.
So the owners won, but it's set at 22. הבעלים נותנים עשרים
ושבע. Habealim notnim beesrim vesheva. בעשרים ושלוש, Beesrim veshalosh, somebody said 23,
so the owners win, but it's set at 23. הבעלים נותנים עשרים
ושמונה. Habealim notnim beesrim veshmonah. בעשרים וארבע, Beesrim vearba, 24, so that
also the owners win, but it's set at 24. הבעלים נותנים עשרים
ותשע. Habealim notnim beesrim vetesha.
They give 29. Now, בעשרים וחמש, Beesrim vechamesh, 25. That should already
be, let's just give it straight to the owners, right? This guy
said 25, the owner said 20. So or let's give it straight
to the other guy. The other guy, I mean not the owner,
the other guy made a higher bid and we don't gain anything
from giving it to the owner, right? Because his 20 plus his
five wouldn't have put him in a higher position.
They're still giving it to the
owner, but he's still paying 30. I know, but again, the only
reason we said the owner won was because his end amount would
have been higher. Here his end amount wouldn't have been higher. So
here we really should give it to the 25 guy. But no,
בעשרים וחמש, Beesrim vechamesh,
the owner still gets it because הקדש Hekdesh gets more. But there's
also מצוה בבעלים. mitzvah babealim.
All right, so the משנה mishna. is ignoring the מצוה בבעלים. mitzvah
babealim. So anyway, let's see what it says. הבעלים נותנים שלושים. Habealim
notnim shloshim. So it actually says, yeah, so we're going to say
it's a tie. So it's a tie, tie goes to the owner
and we win out because then it gets to be the 25
plus the five, it gets to be the 30. שאין מוסיפין חומש
על עילויו של זה. Sheein mosifin chomesh al iluyo shel zeh. Now,
you don't pay a fifth of 25, you still pay only a
fifth of the 20 because you only pay a fifth based on
your bid. But nevertheless, you're stuck with the other guy's setting the
price at 25. של זה. Shel zeh. אמר אחד הרי היא שלי
בעשרים ושש. Amar echad harei hi sheli beesrim veshesh.
All right, now finally. That's why we give them the first bid.
What?
That's why we give them...
yeah, then the owner's additional bid is going to be set only...
right, the
reason, that's a good point too, we want them to bid first
because if he waits and he says let's wait and see, he
won't get into the bidding at all. But now that he's in
the bid, yeah, but it's a real disadvantage to the owner. So
but he might not have a choice, as we said. So he'll
say a dollar maybe. Anyway, somebody else said 26. Now this guy,
26, he should totally win, right? Because even if the owner does
his 20 plus his five, it's 25, so 26 gets more. So
it says here the owner's not forced to win, forced to take
it, but they have an option.
אם רצו הבעלים נותנים שלושים ואחד ודינר. Im ratzu habealim notnim shloshim
veechad vedinar. If they want to give 31 and a dollar, okay,
31 and a little bit, then הבעלים קודמים, habealim kodmim, they can.
Because then by giving 31 and a bit, they're effectively changing their
bid now to have been something like 26, and then they would
have won against this other guy. ואם לאו, Veim lav, and if
they're not interested, אומר לו הרי היא שלך, omer lo harei hi
shelcha, you say to the guy 26, you take it. So the
question is going to be what type of an option is this
for the owner. The other important thing to be aware of, which
it sounds like in the משנה mishna we keep on calling it
an auction, is that it does not sound like you get to
keep on going back and forth, back and forth. It seems like
everybody submits one bid. Okay, that's the impression one gets. A silent
auction, there you go. And as such, the פשט pshat of the
משנה, mishna. although the גמרא gemara will explain it a little differently,
is with the exception of the owner. The owner gets an option
of making a final offer. So if it was 20 and 26,
we would have given it to the guy. But we give the
owner an option in this case of a final offer. If he
made the final offer of 26, right, then 26 and 26, then
he would have, then plus the fifth, then it becomes 31 and
a bit, and we would
have given it to him. But let's assume they tell him what
the other bids were so he can...
Right, right, yes, okay. But anyway, but the simple sense is that
without this last scenario, it's a silent auction. Let's take a look
at the גמרא. gemara. אמר רב חסדא: Amar Rav Chisda: לא שנו
אלא שבין ארבעים עומד במקומו. lo shanu ela shebein arbaim omed binkomo.
When the 50 guy backs out and he pays 10, that's only
if the 40 guy is preparing, is going to actually pay. אבל
אין בין ארבעים עומד במקומו, Aval ein bein arbaim omed binkomo, if
the 40 guy also backs out, now it's not like backs out
at any time, and so we'll get to that in a minute,
משלשין ביניהם, meshalshin beineihem, you have to split it. Because he says
like this, listen to the scenario: 40 guy backed out and 50
guy backed out and 40 guy backed out. So the gap between
40 and 50 we're losing because of the 50 guy backed out,
so he pays 10. But the gap between 40 and 30 we're
losing because who backed out? Both of them backed out. Both of
them are, if either of them had stayed in, we would have
gotten the difference between 40 and 30. So that difference has to
be, each one has half of, has to pay half of that
difference. So five. So the 40 guy pays five and the 50
guy pays 15. That's משלשין ביניהם, meshalshin beineihem, means you divide it
equally between them. Okay, so he says once somebody else backs out,
right, their responsibility, their responsibility like
overlaps. The 50 guy has responsibility from everything until 50, 40 guy
everything until 40, 30 guy everything until 30. So if multiple people
back out, then in those overlapping areas, everybody splits it. Okay,
so the גמרא gemara says like this: מה תנן, Ma tnan, let's
see if that can work in our משנה. mishna תנן, Tnan, our
משנה Mishnah says: חזר בו של ארבעים, משלמין מנכסיו עד עשר, meshalmin
minichasav ad eser, he pays 10.
אמאי, Amai, why is that? ליתי דבן חמשין בהדי, Leteiv deben chamshin
bahadei,
let the 50 guy also participate, pay half of that, right? That's
exactly what you're saying. So the גמרא gemara says: דליכא בן חמישים.
Deleka ben chamishim. No, no, no. The next case is a different
scenario. When we said 50 guy backs out, 40 guy backs out,
those are different cases. One scenario there was a 50 guy and
he backed out. The other scenario there was no 50 guy, there
was only a 40 guy and he backed out, which is again
a little crazy. Number one is why would you need to tell
me all those cases if הלכה halacha is anyway all the same,
and it's certainly not פשט pshat at all. פשט pshat in all
is that they're all in the same auction. Anyway, the גמרא gemara
will eventually reverse it. But first we have to go through the
whole משנה. Mishnah חזר בו בן שלשים, Chazar bo ben shloshim, if
the 30 guy backs out, משלמין מנכסיו עד עשר, meshalmin minichasav ad
eser,
he pays the 10 between 30 and 20. אמאי, Amai, why? ליתי
דבן ארבעים בהדי, Leteiv deben arbaim bahadei, let the 40 guy and
the 50 guy pay with him. דליכא בן ארבעים. Deleka ben arbaim.
No, that next scenario there's no 40 guy, it's only a 30
guy. חזר בו בן עשרים משלמין מנכסיו. Chazar bo ben esrim meshalmin
minichasav. Okay, how about the next, as the commission goes down. 20
guy backs out, he pays עד עשר, he pays 10 between 20
and 10. אמאי, Amai, why? ליתי דבן שלשים בהדי, Leteiv deben shloshim
bahadei, let the 30 guy and the 40 and the 50 guy,
let them all, but okay, we're back to there's only 30. Let
them all participate in that difference. דליכא בן שלשים. Deleka ben shloshim.
No, he's the only guy, only the 20 guy. אי הכי אימא
סיפא. I hachi eima seifa. So if you keep on reading it
in them, the different scenarios and there was nobody higher, let's look
at the last case. חזר בו של עשר, the 10 guy backed
out, מוכרין אותו בשוויו, mocherin oto beshavyo,
you sell it at market rate, ונפרעין משל עשר את המותר. venifra'in
mishel eser es hamotar. You have the 10 guy pay the difference
between market rate and 10.
So ליתי דבן עשרים בהדי, leteiv deben esrim bahadei, so let the
20 guy participate because he also has responsibility. וכי תימא הכא נמי
דליכא בן עשרים, Vechi teima hacha nami deleka ben esrim,
you'll say also this is a case there was only one guy,
only the 10 guy. אי הכי נפרעין משל עשרה, I hachi nifra'in
mishel asara,
why does it say you make the 10 guy pay? It should
say נפרעין ממנו, nifra'in mimenu, you make the guy pay. There's only
one guy according to the way you're reading it, right? You're reading
there's nobody higher. So in the last case, you were left with
the 10, you should have said he has to pay. What do
you mean the 10 has to pay? The 10 has to pay
suggests that there are other people that are part of this auction.
אלא, Ela, so the גמרא gemara finally gives up that read of
the משנה Mishnah which was clearly a very forced read. אלא אמר
רב אשי אלא אמר רב חסדא, Ela amar Rav Ashi ela amar
Rav Chisda, רב חסדא Rav Chisda says: לא קשיא, Lo kashya, it's
not difficult. כאן בבת אחת כאן בזה אחר זה. Kan bevachas kan
beze achar ze. It depends whether it's sequential or at the same
time. If the 50 guy backs out, he pays his difference, 50
and 40, and then he walks away. I'm done with you guys.
I backed out, I paid my difference, I'm done. Now the winner
is 40, it's like 50 guy wasn't here. 40 guy backs out,
he's alone. He pays the difference between 40 and 30. If 40
and 50 back out at the same time, then they're both taking
responsibility, then they're, the responsibility of their actions at that moment has
a consequence. The 50 guy has a consequence even between the gap
of 40 and 30. When the 50 guy backed out and the
40 guy was there at that time, his action only had a
consequence of 10. But if 40 and 50 back out at the
same time, then the 50 guy's backing out at that moment had
a consequence even for the gap of 40 and 30. Now logically,
the גמרא gemara doesn't discuss this, but logically I would say the
same would be true if they backed out in reverse order. So
but maybe you don't give the 40 guy an option to back
out because you don't even talk to him as long as the
50 guy's there. But let's say you did. Let's say the 40
guy could say, you know what, I changed my mind, even if
the 50 guy backs out, I'm out of here. Okay, and then
the 50 guy backed out. So presumably there too, the 50 guy
would pay for the... forty thirty gap because when he backed out,
he's having an impact on the forty.
He didn't pay anything because when
he backed out there was no contract. Oh, that's an interesting perspective.
He backed out with impunity. So anyway, that's it's interesting to speculate
but it's possible that it's a moot question. We don't even pay
attention what the forty guy says is completely irrelevant until the fifty
guy backs out. Okay, so the difference is whether they did it
at the same time or whether it's זה אחר זה. zeh achar
zeh. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: תניא נמי הכי, Tanya
nami hachi, it's similarly, חזרו כולן כאחד, chazru kulan k'echad,
if everybody backed out, not everybody but whatever, or it could be
everybody I guess, משלשין ביניהן, mishalshin beineihen, you
you take the overlaps and every area that's overlapped the people divide
divide equally. So there it says that you do do this equal
division like רב חסדא Rav Chisda said. והאנן תנן, V'ha'anan tnan, ממחזי
נכסיו עד עשרה, mimachzei nechasav ad asarah, don't we say that you
you pay the full amount of the gap between you and the
next guy? אלא לאו שמע מינה Ela lav shma mina לדרב חסדא,
l'deRav Chisda, it must be like רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, that whether
you pay whether you fully pay the gap or everybody pays that
gap that overlaps, it depends whether it was sequential or or at
the same time. שמע מינה. Shma mina. איכא דאמרי לה, Ika d'amri
lah, some explain it we have the problem of the משנה and
the ברייתא Baraita and that רב חסדא Rav Chisda is coming to
answer. We didn't start with רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. רב חסדא Rav
Chisda was an answer. תנן, Tnan, our משנה says חזר בו של
עשרה, chazar bo shel asarah, מוכרין אותו בשבעה וגובה מן של עשרה,
mochrin oto b'shiva v'goveh min shel asarah, את המותר,
that basically you just pay for the gap between you pay the
full amount between the gap of you and the next lowest bid.
ותניא, V'tanya, we have a ברייתא Baraita that says משלשין ביניהן, mishalshin
beineihen, that everybody who has that who was part of that of
that overlap divides it, not just you the last not just you.
אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda, לא קשיא, lo kashya, כאן בבת
אחת כאן בזה אחר זה. kan b'vat achat kan b'zeh achar zeh.
It depends whether it's sequential or at the same time. So again,
again I if I had a whatever something I could draw, but
you can imagine, right? Just imagine overlap. The ten guy goes from
zero to ten. The twenty guy goes from zero to twenty. Like
the thirty guy goes from zero to thirty. So basically what if
they divide at the same time, then every area that people are
overlapping in is divided by all the people that have that overlapped
area because everybody is responsible for that amount. But if it's זה
אחר זה zeh achar zeh sequential, they're only responsible for the amount
that you have stepped away from. Let's just try to because we
got a little behind, sorry, let's just try to read a little
bit more. הבעלים אומרים בעשרים וכל אדם בעשרה. Haba'alim omrim b'esrim v'chol
adam b'asarah. So the גמרא Gemara says למימרא דחומשא עדיף. l'meimra d'chumsha
adif. So the fact that we we go to twenty because we'll
get an additional five and it'll become twenty-five, so we pay attention
to the fifth. Okay, as rather than going to the guy with
the technically higher bid who said
twenty-one. ורמינהו, U'reminhu, I'll ask you, we have a case where we
say the opposite. בעל הבית אומר בסלע ואחר Ba'al habayit omer b'sela
v'acher let's say you're coming to redeem your מעשר שני. Ma'aser Sheni.
And the so you right say my מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni and
I want to redeem it and bring it to ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So
when the owner redeems his מעשר שני, Ma'aser Sheni, he adds a
fifth. Somebody else redeems my מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni and is going
to bring that money to ירושלים, Yerushalayim, which you want to take
it and take it and some געזונטהייט, gezuntheit, he doesn't add right,
he doesn't add a fifth. So what if there's a similar type
of a bidding war as it were? So I say I'll give
a סלע, sela, ואחר אומר, v'acher omer, somebody else says בסלע ואיסר,
b'sela v'issar, a סלע sela and a dollar. So there של סלע
ואיסר קודם, shel sela v'issar kodem, you give it to the guy
that said a סלע sela and a dollar. Why? מפני שמוסיף על
הקרן, mipnei shemosif al hakeren, he has a higher principal. So even
though if I were to redeem it, the total would be higher
because of my fifth, you give it to the guy with the
higher principal. You hear the difference, right? In our משנה you give
it to the owner because the fifth is going to make him
more. Here you give it to the guy that has a higher
principal even though the owner's fifth would have made it more. So
the גמרא Gemara says no, there's an obvious difference of the cases.
הכא דחומשא ריוחא דהקדש הוא חומש עדיף. Hacha d'chumsha rivcha d'hekdesh hu
chumash adif. Here
by who's going to benefit by your additional fifth? In our case,
בית המקדש gets more money. So we're just going to go with
which way is going to get us more money. Okay, so yes,
this guy had a higher had a higher bid, but by going
with the owner it's going to get us more money. So we're
going to go with the owner. התם, Hatam, by by מעשר שני,
Ma'aser Sheni, who benefits from add who what do you do with
the money of מעשר שני? Ma'aser Sheni? What do
you do with the money? Bring it to ירושלים Yerushalayim and you
eat it. So what do we care if it's more or less?
So we have no interest in saying go with the guy that
has more. It's just a simple question of who has the higher
bid. So התם דחומשא רווחא דבעל הבית, hatam d'chumsha ravcha d'ba'al habayit,
there the extra fifth all the money is just what the owner
is going to eat in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So קרנא טפי פריק שפיר
חומשא לא איכפת לן. karna t'fei parik shapir chumsha lo ichpat lan.
We
the principal is what is what is what wins the the bidding.
And who cares about the fifth? The fifth is just something that
the owner adds but we don't have a vested interest in getting
the fifth. So if there's a competition you go by who said
the higher amount. But here we have a vested interest in getting
the higher amount and in getting the fifth, in getting
to the
in getting to the higher amount in our in our bank account
and we will continue with the...